你有在听吗？
Are you paying attention?
很好
Good.
如果你没有仔细听
If you're not listening carefully,
你会错过一些事情
you will miss things,
一些很重要的事情
important things.
我不会停顿
I will not pause.
也不会再说第二遍
I will not repeat myself,
你也不能打断我
and you will not interrupt me.
你以为是你你坐在对面
You think that because you are sitting where you are
而我坐在这里
and I am sitting where I am
以及对即将发生的事都在你的掌控之中
that you are in control of what is about to happen.
你错了
You're mistaken.
是我在掌控
I am in control.
因为我知道你
Because I know things that you
不知道的事
do not know.
曼彻斯特警察局，请稍候
Manchester Police Department,please hold.
我的窗户被打破
Windows broken.
房子被洗劫一空
Home's been ransacked.
能派个警察来吗？
Send a detective down, will you?
我现在需要的是你的
What I will need from you now
一个承诺
is a commitment.
你会仔细听，直到在我说完之前
You will listen closely,and you will not
你不会对我施加评论
judge me until I am finished.
如果你不能承诺这个
If you cannot commit to this,
那请离开这个房间
then please leave the room.
进来
Come in.
但是如果你选择留下
But if you choose to stay,
记住这是你自己的选择
remember you chose to be here.
从这一刻开始
What happens
无论发生什么都不是我的责任
from this moment forwards is not my responsibility.
是你的
It's yours.
请注意听
Pay attention.
这些都是什么？
What's all this, then?
图灵，艾伦
Turing, Alan.
剑桥的教授
Professor at King's.
似乎是入室抢劫
Seems there's been a burglary.
哦？丢了什么？
Oh? What of?
嗯，好像什么也没丢，真的
Well, that's just it.Nothing missing, really.
他在曼彻斯特做什么？
What's he doing in Manchester?
做一些与机器有关的事
Something with machines.
一个国家物理实验室的项目
The project at the NPL.
我问了，但他不肯具体说是什么
I checked, but he won't say what it's on.
图灵教授？
Professor Turing?
努克警察，曼彻斯特警察局
Detective Nook,Manchester Police.
中士史泰利告诉我你家昨晚被盗
Sergeant Staehl here tells me you had a burglary last night.
图灵教授？
Professor Turing?
退后一步
Take a step back,
不要大力呼吸
and don't breath heavily.
-呼吸？         -未稀释的氰化物
- Breathe?      - Undiluted cyanide.
它-它只要
It-it wouldn't take
少量就能杀了你
more than a thimbleful to kill you.
啊
Ah.
真是令人失望
Disappointing.
什么？
Pardon?
我希望的不一样
L-I had hoped for a bit more.
中士史泰利，难道只是我觉得，或者你也感觉到
Sergeant Staehl, is it just me,or do you get the sense
我们被侮辱了？
that we're being insulted?
昨晚，你被盗了
Last night, you had a break-in.
你的邻居，斯普林博先生，打电话报告了噪音
Your neighbor, Mr. Springborn,called to report the noise.
他说有不少的骚动
He said there was quite a ruckus.
可是你说什么也没丢
Only you say nothing was taken.
很奇怪，所以不如你告诉我们
It's odd.So how about you tell us
发生什么事了，我们会找出是谁做的
what happened, and we'll find the chap who did this.
先生们
Gentlemen,
我不认为
I-I don't believe
你们能找出是谁做的
that you could find the chap that did this
除非，呃，他走向你对你的脸吐口水
if, uh, he walked up to you and spat in your face.
我现在需要的
Uh, what I could us right now
不是警察，而是一个好的清洁女工
is not a bobby,but a really good cleaning lady.
除非你的车里有
So unless one of you has a-an apron
一条围裙，我建议
in your car, I suggest
带上你的文件报告离开别烦我
you file your reports and leave me alone.
就像你说的，图灵教授
As you say, Professor Turing.
祝你的氰化物好运
Best of luck with your cyanide.
我会给你一磅
I'll give you a quid
如果你能给出比这更加难以忍受的家伙的名字
if you can name me a more insufferable sod.
似乎有点勉强，不过，不是吗？
Seemed a bit forced,though, didn't it?
不知道你在说什么
Don't know what you mean.
嗯，如果你不想一对警察
Well, if you didn't want a pair of bobbies
挖掘你的私事
digging around in your personal affairs,
这是一个主要的方式来确保他们不这样做
that'd have been a stellar way to make sure they don't.
告诉我，你不认为这很可疑吗
Tell me you don't think this is suspicious.
我不认为这很可疑
I don't think this is suspicious.
一个神秘的教授为什么不承认
A mysterious professor who won't admit
有人已经从他家里偷了东西？
he's had something stolen from his house?
我认为艾伦图灵
I think Alan Turing's
隐藏了些什么
hiding something.
战争爆发了！
War declared!
80万个孩子撤离！
800,000 children evacuated!
德国正在进攻！
German bombs on their way!
卖报了！
Get your papers here!
新鲜出炉的新闻！
Fresh off the press!
战争爆发了！
War declared!
80万个孩子撤离！
800,000 children evacuated!
德国随时进攻！
German bombs expected soon!
今天上午
This morning,
英国驻柏林大使
the British Ambassador in Berlin
交给德国政府
handed the German government
最后警示
a final note stating that
除非我们到11:00前得到
unless we heard from them,
他们的回复
by 11:00,
不然就承认战争状态
a state of war
存在我们两国之间
would exist between us.
我现在要告诉你
I have to tell you now
目前还没有收到任何回复
that no such undertaking has been received.
因此
And that, consequently,
这个英国与德国正处于
this country is at war
战争状态
with Germany.
在我们大多数人的生活
For the second time
这是我们
in the lives of most of us,
第二次...
we are...
处于战争之中
at war.
……去寻找
...to find
一个和平的出路…
a peaceful way out...
请出示证件
Papers, please.
你在这里做什么？
What are you doing here?
哦，呃，那位女士告诉我等着
Oh, uh,the lady told me to wait.
在我的办公室？
In my office?
她有没有告诉你可以
She tell you to help yourself to tea
边等边喝茶？
while you were here?
呃，不，她没有
Uh, no, she didn't.
她显然没有告诉你
She obviously didn't tell you
这是个笑话不是吗?
what a joke was, then,either, I gather.
她应该说吗？
Was she supposed to?
你是谁？
Who are you?
艾伦图灵
Alan Turing.
啊，图灵
Ah, Turing.
那位数学家
The mathematician.
是的
Correct.
- 我是怎么猜到的呢？               - 嗯，你没猜出来
- However could I have guessed?    - Well, you didn't.
你只是读了那张纸
You just read it on that piece of paper.
皇家学院，剑桥
King's College, Cambridge.
好吧，这里说你是个天才
Now, it says here you were a bit of a prodigy
在数学系
in the maths department.
我不确定我能评价这个，先生...
L-I'm not sure I can evaluate that, Mr...
-你多大了，图灵先生？             -嗯，27。
- How old are you, Mr. Turing?    - Uh, 27.
你几岁时在剑桥成为一个研究员？
And how old were you when you became a Fellow at Cambridge?
- 24       - 当你发表这篇我不太懂的
- 24.      - And how old were you
题目的文章时
when you published this paper that has a title
你多大？
I can barely understand?
-呃，23     -你不觉得
- Uh, 23.   - And you don't think
你有资格作为一个公认的天才？
that qualifies you as a certified prodigy?
嗯，牛顿22岁时发现了二项式定理
Well, Newton discovered binomial theorem aged 22.
爱因斯坦写了四篇论文，改变了世界
Einstein wrote four papers that changed the world
在他26岁的时候
by the age of 26.
据我所知
As far as I can tell,
我
I've...
我勉强不能相提并论
I've barely made par.
天啊，你真严肃
My God, you're serious.
难道你喜欢我开玩笑？
Would you prefer I made a joke?
哦，我想你不知道那是什么
Oh, I don't think you know what those are.
如果这是在工作的要求，
Hardly seems fair that，that's a requirement
这太不公平了，你是？
for employment here, Mr...
丹尼斯顿指挥官,皇家海军
Commander Denniston,Royal Navy.
好的，图灵先生，我引起了我的兴趣
All right,Mr. Turing, I'll bite.
你为什么要为国王陛下的政府工作？
Why do you wish to work for His Majesty's government?
哦，我不想，真的
Oh, I don't, really.
你是一个该死的和平主义者？
Are you a bleeding pacifist?
我是..关于暴力的不可知论者
I'm... agnostic about violence.
好的，你知道
Well, you do realize
距离伦敦600英里远
that 600 miles away from London
有个讨厌的混蛋叫希特勒
there's this nasty little chap called Hitler
想对欧洲实行专制？
who wants to engulf Europe in tyranny?
政治不是我的专长
Politics isn't really my area of expertise.
真的？
Really?
好吧，我相信你刚刚在英国军事史
Well, I believe you've just set the record
创下一个最短的
for the shortest job interview
面试纪录
in British military history.
哦，呃…
Oh, uh...
妈妈说由于作为一个在世界上最好的数学家
Mother says I can be off-putting sometimes on account
有时我会令人讨厌
of being one of the best mathematicians in the world.
在这个世界上？
In the world?
哦，是的
Oh, yes.
你知道我为这计划已经拒绝了有多少人？
Do you know how many people I've rejected for this program?
- 不知道   -嗯，没错
- No.      - Well, that's right,
因为这是一个绝密计划
because we're a top-secret program.
但我要告诉你，只是因为我们是朋友
But I'll tell you,just because we're friends,
就在上星期
that only last week,
我拒绝了我们国家的一个顶级的语言学家
I rejected one of our great nation's top linguists.
比贝托尔特·布莱希特德语还要好
Knows German better than Bertolt Brecht.
我不说德语
I don't speak German.
什么？
What?
我不
I don't...
说德语
speak German.
那么，你是怎么解密
Well, how the hell were you supposed to decrypt
德国通讯如果你不...
German communications if you don't...
我不知道，说德语吗？
I don't know, speak German?
嗯，我真的很擅长填字游戏
Well, I'm really quite excellent at crossword puzzles.
-玛格丽特！    -德国的代码是一个迷
- Margaret!    - The German codes are a puzzle.
是个游戏，就像任何其他的游戏
A game, just like any other game.
- 玛格丽特，你在哪里？        - 我真的很擅长游戏
- Margaret, where are you?    - I'm really very good at games.
呃，谜
Uh, puzzles.
这是世界上最难的谜
And this is the most difficult puzzle in the world.
玛格丽特！
Margaret!
看在上帝的份上
For the love of God.
显然这是一个笑话
This is a joke, obviously.
恐怕我不知道那是什么
I'm afraid I don't know what those are,
丹尼斯顿指挥官
Commander Denniston.
祝你回到剑桥的旅程愉快，教授
Have a pleasant trip back to Cambridge, Professor.
英格玛
Enigma.
你叫我？
You called for me?
这就是你在这里做的事
That's what you're doing here.
在布莱奇利的绝密计划
The top-secret program at Bletchley.
你试图破解德国的英格玛密码机
You're trying to break the German Enigma machine.
你为什么这么觉得？
What makes you think that?
这是历史上最伟大的加密装置
It's the greatest encryption device in history,
德国所有的主要通信都用它
and the Germans use it for all major communications.
如果盟军破解了英格玛
If the Allies broke Enigma,
那么
well
这会变成一个很短的战争，显然的
This would turn into a very short war, indeed.
当然这是你的工作
Of course that's what you're working on.
但你还没得到任何头绪
But you also haven't got anywhere with it.
如果你有，你就不会从
If you had, you wouldn't be hiring cryptographers
大学招聘解密者
out of university.
你需要我比我更需要你
Y- You need me a lot more than I need you.
我喜欢解决问题
L-I like solving problems,
指挥官
Commander.
而英格玛是世界上最难的问题
And Enigma is the most difficult problem in the world.
不，英格玛并不难；是不可破解的
No, Enigma isn't difficult;it's impossible.
美军，俄军，法军
The Americans, the Russians,the French,
德军，每个都认为英格玛
the Germans,everyone thinks Enigma
是牢不可破的
is unbreakable.
好的
Good.
让我试试，我们会知道答案的
Let me try,and we'll know for sure,
不是吗？
won't we?
英格玛欢迎你
Welcome to Enigma.
所有突然袭击的细节
The details of every surprise attack,
所有秘密护航的任务
every secret convoy
所有在大西洋的深海潜艇的
and every U-boat in the bloody Atlantic
都输入在里面
go into that thing.
然后吐出无意义数据
And out comes gibberish.
它很漂亮
It's beautiful.
这是死亡的狡猾操作手
It's the crooked hand of death itself.
皇家女子海军每天拦截无线电信息成千上万
Our Wrens intercept thousands of radio messages a day,
对于这些可爱的年轻女士
and to the lovely young ladies
这都是胡说八道
of the Women's Royal Navy,they're nonsense.
只有当你把这些返回到英格玛
It's only when you feed them back into Enigma
他们才使它有意义
that they make any sense.
但我们只有一个英格玛密码机
But we have an Enigma machine.
没错，波兰情报局
Yes, Polish Intelligence
从柏林偷的
smuggled it out of Berlin.
有什么问题吗？
So what's the problem?
把截获的消息
Just put the intercepted messages
返回到英格玛就可以…
back into the Enigma and you'll...
没想象中那么简单不是吗？
Look, it's not that simple, is it?
只有一个英格玛密码机
Just having an Enigma machine
是不能帮你解码信息的
doesn't help you to decode the messages.
很好，图灵先生
Very good, Mr. Turing.
解码信息，你需要知道这个机器的设定
To decode a message, you need to know the machine's settings.
现在，德国会在每天早上
Now, the Germans switch settings
变换设定
every day promptly at midnight.
我们通常拦截的
We usually intercept
第一个信息在早上6:00
our first message around 6:00 a.m.,
在它变化之前
which gives you exactly
会给你每天18小时
18 hours every day to crack the code
破解密码，不然你得重新开始
before it changes,and you start again.
五个转子
Five rotors.
十个插接电缆
Ten plugboard cables.
-一百万…            - 几十亿…
- One million...     - A thousand million...
不，不，这是，呃，我知道了
No, no, it's,uh, I've got it.
这是万亿，这显然是几百万
It's million, million. It's in the millions, obviously.
这是超过150百万亿种可能的设定
It's over 150 million million million possible settings.
非常好
Very good.
159.
如果你想确切的说，1-5-9
If you want to be exact about it. 1-5-9
背后有18个零
with 18 zeroes behind it.
的可能性
Possibilities.
每一天
Every single day.
先生们，休 亚力山大
Gentlemen, meet Hugh Alexander.
我亲自选择了他
I personally selected him
-管理这个团队         -你是不是…
- to run this unit.   - Didn't you...
亚力山大先生赢得了英国的全国象棋锦标赛
Mr. Alexander won Britain's national chess championship.
两次
Twice.
你不是这里唯一一个
You're not the only one
擅长游戏的，图灵
who's good at games around here, Turing.
我们今后要一起工作吗？
Are-are we to work together, then?
我喜欢有自己的办公室
I prefer to have my own office.
你们是一个团队，而你是其中一份子
You're a team,and you will work as one.
我不想花时间解释我自己的思路
I-I-I don't have time to explain myself as I go along,
我怕这些人
and I'm afraid these men
- 会拖累我                     - 如果你不能
- would only slow me down.      - If you can't
与我们一起，那恐怕我们不能让你参加
play together, then I'm afraid we can't let you play at all.
这是斯图尔特 孟席斯，军情六处
This is Stewart Menzies, MI6.
只有五个师的军事情报
There are only five divisions of military intelligence.
没有军情六处
There is no MI6.
没错
Exactly.
那是官方解释
That's the spirit.
图灵先生，你知道有多少英国军人
Mr. Turing, do you know how many British servicemen
因为英格玛死了？
have died because of Enigma?
呃，不，我不知道
Uh, no, I don't.
三个...
Three...
当我们进行
while we've been having
这段对话时
this conversation.
哦，看，又有一个
Oh, look, there's another.
我希望他没有家庭
I rather hope he didn't have a family.
指挥官丹尼斯顿谈论的这场战争
This war Commander Denniston's been going on about,
我们没有赢
we're not winning it.
破解密码
Break the code,
至少使我们有一个机会去赢
at least we have a chance.
我们让孩子玩玩独自
Shall we leave the children alone
他们的新玩具？
with their new toy?
嗯
Hm.
好了，先生们…
All right, gentlemen...
我们开始吧
let's play.
游戏很简单
The game was quite a simple one.
每一个德国情报，每一个突袭
Every single German message,every surprise attack,
每一个轰炸
every bombing run,
每一个即将到来的潜艇攻击…
every imminent U-boat assault...
他们都在空中传播
They were all floating through the air.
通过无线电信号…
Radio signals that...
好吧，任何一个学生仔只要有无线电
well, any schoolboy with an AM kit
都可以拦截
could intercept.
诀窍是加密的信息
The trick was that they were encrypted.
有159百万亿的可能性
There were 159 million million million possible
的英格玛设定
Enigma settings.
我们要做的就是尝试每一种可能性
All we had to do was try each one.
但是，如果我们有十人检查一个设定要一分钟
But if we had ten men checking one setting a minute
每天24小时，每周七天，
for 24 hours every day and seven days every week,
你认为它会多少天呢，呃，去检查
how many days do you think it would take to, uh, to check
每个设置？
each of the settings?
那不是以天计的，是以年计
Well, it's not days, it's years.
早上好
Good morning.
这将花掉2千万年
It's 2O million years.
-去阻止即将到来的攻击           - 谢谢
- To stop a coming attack,      - Thank you.
我们必须将这2千万的时间
We would have to check 2O million years' worth
精确到
of settings
在2O分钟内
in 2O minutes.
我饿了
I'm famished.
吃午饭吗？
Lunch?
天哪，那些戴小帽子的
Good Lord. What is it
女人是做什么的？
about women with little hats?
伙计，我们去吃午饭
The boys, we're going to get some lunch.
艾伦？
Alan?
嗯哼？
Yes'?
我说我们去吃午饭
I said we're going to get some lunch.
艾伦？
Alan?
怎么了？
Yes'?
- 你有听见我说话吗？       -有啊
- Can you hear me?         - Yes.
我说我们要去吃午...
I said we're off to get some lu...
这开始有点死循环了
This is starting to get a little bit repetitive.
-什么？           - 我问你
- What is?          - I had asked
要不要跟我们一起吃午餐
if you wanted to come to lunch with us.
嗯，没有，你没有
Um, no, you didn't.
你说你要去吃午饭。
You said you were going to get some lunch.
我哪里得罪你了？
Have I offended you in some way?
你怎么会这么想？
Why would you think that?
你要跟我们一起吃午餐吗？
Would you like to come to lunch with us?
- 什么时间吃午饭？         -天啊，艾伦
- What time's lunchtime?    - Christ, Alan,
就是一个该死的三明治
it's a bleeding sandwich.
-拿来干嘛？          - 当午餐
- What is?           - Lunch.
哦，我不喜欢三明治
Oh, I don't like sandwiches.
算了
Never mind.
你知道，
You know,
要战胜这套天才的加密程序
to pull off this irascible genius routine,
采取的方式也得是天才式的，艾伦
one actually has to be a genius, Alan.
而我们
And yet we're the ones
已经有了进展，不是吗？
making progress here,aren't we?
哦，是吗？
Oh, you are?
是的，我们有
Yes, we are.
我们已经解密的一些德国的消息
We have decrypted a number of German messages
通过对字母的分布频率
by analyzing the frequency of letter distribution.
哦，即使是一个坏时钟一天也有两次正确的时候
Oh, even a broken clock is right twice a day.
那不是进步；那只是运气
That-That's not progress;that's just blind luck.
我正在设计的机器
I'm designing a machine
可以让我们每天即时
that will allow us to break every message
破解每条情报
every day instantly.
谁饿了？
Who's hungry?
我们走吧
Let's go.
我饿了—
I'm hungry-
什么？
What?
彼得问谁饿了
Peter asked who was hungry.
可以给我带些汤吗？
Can I have some soup, please?
你什么意思，“保密”？
What do you mean, "classified"?
不，我知道保密这个词的字面意义
No, I'm aware of the literal meaning of the word classified.
我问的是为什么一个数学教授
What I'm asking is why would a maths professor
他的军事记录需要保密？
have his military records classified?
嗯，好吧，我会冷静
Yeah, well, I will come down.
对不起，我想看一些文件，如果我可以的话
Pardon me, I'd like to see some documents, if I may.
图灵先生服役记录
Service records of a Mr. Turing.
艾伦
Alan.
外交部交给我的
Foreign Office sent me.
这是不可接受的
This is unacceptable.
如果你想讨论投诉
If you wish to discuss the complaint,
我建议你预约一下
I suggest you make a proper appointment.
亚历山…
Alexan...
投诉？
Complaint?
不，不，休 亚力山大
No, no, Hugh Alexander
已经否绝我申请配件
has denied my requisition for parts
和设备，我需要建设我所设计的机器
and-and equipment that I need to build the machine I've designed.
你的同事拒绝与你的工作
Your fellow code-breakers are refusing to work with you,
他们提出正式投诉
and they filed a formal complaint.
它的灵感来自一个古老的波兰码机
It's is inspired by an old Polish code machine.
只有这个是极大的进步
Only this one is infinitely more advanced.
如果你不回应投诉
If you don't respond to the complaint,
我不得不把他们带回内政部
I shall have to take it up with the Home Office.
把文件放在我的桌上
Put those files by my desk.
好的，我的回答是他们都是白痴
Fine, my response is they're all idiots.
解雇他们用剩下的钱来资助我的机器
Fire them and use the savings to fund my machine.
我只需要大约十万英磅
I only need about 100,000 pounds.
十万英磅…
100,000...
你为什么要造一个机器？
Why are you building a machine?
这是高科技，你不会明白的
It's highly technical.You wouldn't understand.
我建议你还是试着说清楚
I suggest you make the effort to try.
英格玛是...
Enigma is...
一个非常精心设计的机器
an extremely well-designed machine.
我们的问题是我们只能用人尝试去击败它
Our problem is that we're only using men to try to beat it.
不，如果有一台机器
No, what if only a machine
能击败另一台机器呢？
can defeat another machine?
嗯，也不是很高科技
Well, that's not very technical.
休 亚力山大才是
Hugh Alexander is in charge
你的主管；他说不，那就是不
of your unit; he said no,and that is that.
我只是没时间了
I simply don't have time for this.
你有没有赢过一场战争，图灵？
Have you ever won a war, Turing?
我有
I have.
你知道如何做？
Do you know how it's done?
秩序，纪律，
Order, discipline,
严格服从
chain of command.
你不再是在大学
You're not at university any longer.
你是一个非常大的系统的一个非常小的齿轮
You are a very small cog in a very large system.
你要服从你上级的命令
And you will do as your commanding officer instructs.
好的
Yes.
谁是你们的指挥官？
Who-who is your commanding officer?
温斯顿丘吉尔
Winston Churchill,
唐宁街10号
Number 1O Downing Street,
伦敦，邮编SW1
London, SW1 .
我的决定有什么问题
You have a problem with my decision,
你可以去找他
you can take it up with him.
孟席斯先生！
Mr. Menzies!
你会去伦敦吗？
A-A-Are you going to London?
可能会
Possibly.
你能为我送一封信？
Would you deliver a letter for me?
看，我很抱歉
Look, I'm sorry,
但是，你在开玩笑吗？
but are you joking?
丘吉尔让艾伦主管？
Churchill's put Alan in charge?
- 这是一个可怕的决定         -不，不，不，不，不行。
- This is a terrible idea.   - No, no, no, no, no.
所以我可以给这些人下命令？
So I can give these men orders now?
我恨这样说，不过是的
I hate to say it, but yes.
太好了，基思和查尔斯，你们被解雇了
Excellent. Keith and Charles,you're both fired.
-你说什么？    -什么？
- Excuse me?   - What?
你是平庸的语言学家
You're mediocre linguists,
可怜的解密者
and positively poor code-breakers.
艾伦，你不能开除基思和查尔斯
Alan, you can't just fire Keith and Charles.
嗯，他刚刚说我可以
Well, he just said I could.
不，我没有这样说
No, I did no such thing.
但丘吉尔这样说了
But Churchill did.
见鬼去吧
Go to hell.
嗯
Well,
这是不人道的
this is inhuman.
即使是你
Even for you.
在学校受欢迎，是吗？
Popular at school, were you?
问题出现，当然
The problem began, of course,
从胡萝卜开始
with the carrots.
胡萝卜是橙色的
Carrots are orange.
豌豆
And peas
是绿色的
are green.
他们不能混在一起
They mustn't touch.
我来
I got it.
你知道人们为什么
Do you know why people
喜欢暴力吗？
like violence?
这是因为让人感觉…
It is because it feels...
很好
good.
人类发现暴力
Humans find violence
能带来强烈的满足感
deeply satisfying.
但除了满足感
But remove the-the satisfaction,
这些行为变得…
and the act becomes...
异常空虚
hollow.
图灵？
Tuflng?
拜托
Come on.
别像个犹太人一样
Don't be such a kike about it.
让他该死的在这腐烂吧
Leave him to bloody rot.
我没有靠我自己学会这个
I didn't learn this on my own,
当然
of course.
有人帮助
I had help.
克里斯托弗会帮我
Christopher helped.
艾伦，你还好吗？
Alan, are you all right?
这不是我的错
It's not my fault.
胡萝卜跟豌豆和混在一起…
The carrots got in with the peas and...
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我不会让他们再这样做了
I won't let them do it again.
他们越来越狠了
They're getting worse.
他们打我，因为我比他们更聪明
They only beat me up because I'm smarter than they are.
不，他们打你因为你不同
No, they beat you up because you're different.
妈妈说，我只是一个怪胎
Mother says I'm just an odd duck.
她是对的
And she's right.
但你知道吗，艾伦
But you know, Alan,
有时候正是人们意想不到之人
sometimes it's the very people who no one imagines anything of
做出了人们意想不到之事
who do the things no one can imagine.
那，我们现在做什么？
So, what do we do now?
我们人手不够
We're short on staff.
那，我们，呃，就去找
Well, we, uh, we get
更多的人来
more staff then.
你打算怎么做？
And how do you propose to do that?
呃，艾伦图灵
Um, Alan Turing
来见斯图尔特孟席斯
to see Stewart Menzies.
好的，先生
Very good, sir.
他们都是谁？
So who are they?
哦，各种各样，真的
Oh, all sorts, really.
有老师，工程师
Teacher, an engineer,
少数学生
a handful of students.
你认为他们有资格为布莱奇利工作
And you think they're qualified for Bletchley
是因为他们擅长拼字游戏吗？
'cause they're good at crossword puzzles?
嗯，他们说他们很擅长，现在我们就来测试一下
Well, they say they're good,and now we shall find out,
不是吗？
don’t we？
为了帮助你们
In order to aid your efforts,
这里，你的右手边，一个绿色的刮卡书
there is, to the right of you,a green scratch card book.
你可以在上面做笔记
You are to make notes in that.
先生们，你们有六分钟的时间
Gentlemen, you have six minutes
完成填字，在这一点上
in which to complete the puzzle, at which point,
我将…
I will...
对不起，夫人，这个房间不能随便进入
Pardon, ma'am,this room's restricted.
哦，不好意思我迟到了
Oh, apologies for my tardiness.
我坐的巴士爆胎了
The-the bus caught a flat tire.
嗯，我可以继续吗？
Uh, may I continue, please?
-谢谢你            - 你不能待在这儿，夫人
- Thank you.       - You're not allowed in here, ma'am.
哦，但我只迟到了几分钟
Oh, but I'm only a few minutes late.
你可以去找楼上的秘书
The secretaries are to head upstairs.
这个房间只对候选人开放
This room's for the candidates.
我现在可以继续吗？
May I get on with this now, please?
我是一个候选人
L-I am a candidate.
什么职位？
For what position?
信中没有说具体
The letter didn't say precisely.
是啊，所以先上楼去找秘书
Yeah, so secretaries are to head upstairs.
他说这是最高机密
It did say that it was top secret.
到底是怎么回事？
What is going on?
我解开了
L-I solved
报纸上的一个填字游戏
a-a crossword puzzle in the newspaper,
然后收到这封信时说
and I-l got this letter saying
我被选为某个神秘工作的候选人
that I was a candidate for some sort of mysterious job.
我的名字是琼 克拉克
My name's Joan Clarke.
小姐，你真的是自己解开这个难题吗？
Miss, did you really solve this puzzle yourself?
是什么让你认为我不能自己解开？
What makes you think I couldn't solve the puzzle myself?
-我真的很擅长…                    -夫人
- L-I'm really very good at...     - Ma'am,
-我要问你…                          - 克拉克小姐
- I'll have to ask you to...         - Miss Clarke,
我想迟到
I-I find tardiness
在任何情况下，嗯，都是不可接受的
under any circumstance,um, unacceptable.
请坐，我们继续
Take a seat so that ，we may continue.
谢谢
Thank you.
现在，嗯
Now, um,
正如我说的，你有六分钟
as I was saying,you-you have six minutes
去，呃，去解开你桌上的填字
to, uh, complete the task in front of you.
嗯，先生们和夫人
Uh, gentlemen and lady,
可以开始了
begin.
六分钟
Six minutes.
这可能吗？
Is that even possible?
不可能，我花了八分钟
No, it takes me eight.
这不是填字游戏
This isn't about crossword puzzles.
这是关于一个，呃
It's about how one, uh,
解决一个不可能的问题的方法
approaches solving an impossible problem.
你解决是一次性全部解决还是
Do you tackle the whole thing at once or divide it
分成不同小部分..。
into small...
你完成了？
You've finished?
是的。
Yes.
5分34秒
Five minutes and 34 seconds.
你说要在六分钟内
You said to do it in under six.
祝贺你
Congratulations.
我热烈的欢迎你们为陛下服务
My warmest welcome to His Majesty's service.
如果你说一个字关于我要给你说的
If you speak a word of what I'm about to show you,
你将会以叛国罪被处决
you will be executed for high treason.
你要欺骗你的朋友
You will lie to your friends,
你的家人和你遇到的每个人
your family and everyone you meet
关于你真正做的是什么
about what it is you really do.
那我们真正在做的是什么?
And what is it that we're really doing?
我们要破解一个牢不可破的纳粹代码
We're going to break an unbreakable Nazi code
来赢得战争
and win the war.
哦
Oh.
你正在看什么书？
What's that you're reading?
关于加密技术的
It's about cryptography.
比如秘密信息？
Like secret messages?
不是秘密
Not secret.
这便是高明之处
That's the brilliant part.
任何人都可以看到的消息，但是没有人知道他们是什么意思
Messages that anyone can see,but no one knows what they mean
除非你有钥匙
unless you have the key.
和交谈有什么不同吗？
How's that different from talking?
- 交谈？            - 当人们彼此交谈
- Talking?          - When people talk to each other,
他们从不说他们的真实想法
they never say what they mean.
他们说的是别的
They say something else,
但是他们希望你能理解他们要表达的是什么意思
and you're expected to just know what they mean.
只有我不懂
Only I never do.
那么，有什么不一样？
So, how's that different?
艾伦，我有一个很奇怪的感觉
Alan, I have a funny feeling
你会很擅长这个
you're going to be very good at this.
晚安，艾伦
Good night, Alan.
晚安
Good night.
等等，玛丽恩，我来了！
Hold on,Marion, I'm coming!
通过这个小的设置然后沿路线返回...
Coming round the lesser settings and then route back through...
回到这里…
Back to those ones...
呃，小心点，好吗？
Uh, careful, will you?
嗯，这不是一个玩具
Um, it-it's not a toy.
有趣
Funny.
这看起来就像个玩具
Looks like a toy.
这就是那该死的要花十万英镑的东西
Bloody great 100,000-pound one.
你的新宠物的到了
Your new minion's arrived.
杰克 古德，我们见…
Jack Good. We met...
嗯，克拉克小姐在哪里？
Well, where's Miss Clarke?
很可爱，不是吗？
Lovely, isn't he?
这不只是个单调乏味的生产厂
It's not just a-a usual humdrum production mill factory.
我的意思是，嗯，就像我说的
I mean, well,as-as I was saying,
这是一个非常重要的，呃，无线电厂
it's a very important,uh, radio factory.
它不是，事实上，嗯，嗯，嗯
I-It's not, actually.Uh, well, um,
是辐射方面的，呃...无线电工厂
on the spectrum of,uh... radio factories,
这是一个非常特别…
this-this one is-is particularly...
你为什么不在布莱奇利？
Why are you not at Bletchley?
非常…感谢你的拜访，图灵先生
Thank you... so much for your visit, Mr. Turing.
-你旅途愉快吗？                -收拾你的东西然后我们离开这里
- Was your trip pleasant?      - Gather your things and let's go.
对不起，我无法接受你的提议
I'm sorry, but I'm unable to accept your offer.
我们认为这样一个职位
We feel that such a position
不是很适合我
would hardly be appropriate.
你获得了双第一在数学上
You earned a double first in mathematics.
但遗憾的是没有获得机会成为一个研究员
But sadly wasn't granted the opportunity to become a Fellow.
你属于布莱奇利
You belong at Bletchley.
我很抱歉，为了我的这个职位
I'm sorry,but for someone in my position
我需要...
to live... to...
离家很远去无线电厂
to work in a radio factory so far from home,
和你手下的男人生活、工作，呃...
with all your men, um...
那将...
it-it would be...
有失体统
indecorous.
那在这个世界还有什么意义？
What in the world does that even mean?
我们有一组，呃，年轻的女士
We have a group of,uh, young ladies
负责我们所有的
who tend to all of our
文书工作：助理，翻译
clerical tasks:assistants, translators.
嗯，他们住在一起，嗯，在城里
Uh, they live,um, together in town.
这-这-这会是一个更，呃，合适的环境？
W-W-Would that be a more,uh, suitable environment?
嗯，所以我会在这些妇女中工作？
Hm. So-so I would be working amongst these women?
是的
Yes.
都是优秀的女士们，嗯，他们甚至还组织社会活动
Wonderful ladies. Uh, they even organize social events
在圣马丁教堂下的路上
at St. Martin's Church down the road.
嗯，真的，整个事情是非常，呃…
Uh, really, the whole thing is-is quite, uh...
怎么说…
uh, um...
端庄
decorous.
现在，你不会有不适当的安全检查
Now, you won't have proper security clearance,
当然，因此，呃，我们将不得不凑合一些事情
of course, so, uh, we'll have to improvise things a bit.
你为什么要帮我？
Why are you helping me?
因为现在在这整个世界
Because there is only one thing that matters
只有一件东西是重要的...你明白吗？
in this entire world right now... do you understand?...
就是破解英格玛
and that is breaking Enigma.
但是，图灵先生…
But-but, Mr. Turing...
你为什么要帮我？
why are you helping me?
哦，呃…
Oh. Um...
因为有时候正是人们意想不到之人
sometimes it's the very people who no one imagines anything of
做出了人们意想不到之事
who do the things that no one can imagine.
先生
Sir.
这是什么？
What's this?
艾伦图灵的机密军事文件
Alan Turing's classified military file.
- 这是空的              -没错
- It's bloody empty.    - Exactly.
-这是一个空的信封                       -是的
- It's an empty manila envelope.        - Yeah.
嗯，你不是已经破案了吗？
Well, you've cracked the case wide open, then, haven't you?
艾伦图灵的战争记录的不仅是机密
Alan Turing's war records aren't just classified,
他们是不存在的
they're nonexistent.
那意味着有人销毁了他们
That means someone's got rid of them.
抹去档案，烧点一切
Erased them.Burned them.
是那个闯进他家什么也没有偷的人干的？
And that same person broke into his house and stole nothing?
盖伊伯吉斯和唐纳德麦克莱恩
Guy Burgess and Donald Maclean.
怎么，写文章的间谍？
What the spies from the papers?
苏联间谍
The Soviet spies.
但首先他们是教授，不是吗？
But first they were professors, weren't they?
在剑桥很激进
Radicalized at Cambridge,
然后他们加入了共产党
then they joined the Communist Party,
对外办公，在战争期间泄露信息
then Foreign Office,then leaked information
给斯大林...现在
to Stalin during the war... now
你能想到我们所知道的人谁在剑桥过
can you think of anyone else we know who was at Cambridge,
而且在战争爆发时泄露了一些黑暗和绝密的信息？
then took up something murky and top secret when war broke out?
你认为这个艾伦可能是一个苏联特工？
You think this Alan Turing might be a Soviet agent?
我认为…
I think...
将要有很严重的事情发生
something very serious is happening
就在我们的鼻子底下
right here under our noses.
难道你不想找出它是什么？
Wouldn't you like to find out what it is?
欢迎，女士们
Welcome, ladies.
请跟我来
If you'd like to follow me.
有些人认为我们与德国
Some people thought we were at war
打战...是不正确的
with the Germans... incorrect.
我们分分秒秒都在战争中
We were at war with the clock.
英国简直快饿死了
Britain was literally starving to death.
美国人每星期会送
The Americans sent over
十万吨的食物过来，是的，每星期
100,000 tons of food every week,and, uh, every week
然后德国人会把我们迫切需要的面包
the Germans would send our desperately needed bread
炸到海底
to the bottom of the ocean.
我们失败都会在午夜时刻知晓
Our daily failure was announced at the chimes of midnight.
这声音萦绕着我们悲伤的梦想
And the sound would haunt our unwelcome dreams.
滴...
Tick...
答...
tock...
滴
tick.
真该死！
Damn it!
- 怎么了？                      - 到午夜了…
- What just happened?            - Midnight...
我们所做的一切都是无用功
all the work we've done today is useless.
哦，别担心，我们还有几个小时
Oh, but don't worry,we've a few hours
在明天的消息开始泛滥…
before tomorrow's messages start flooding in...
和我们重新开始之前
and we start all over again.
从零开始
From scratch.
我讨厌这样
I'm so sick of this.
花了四小时重装他的插板矩阵
Four hours rewiring his plugboard matrix.
昨天花了三小时
Three hours yesterday
在他的转子的位置上！
on his rotor positions!
-不要去那边                       - 听着，约翰，不
- Don't go over there.            - Look, John, no.
如果之前没人说这个工作无法完成
If this job wasn't already impossible before,
- 该死的现在就是              - 休，不要
- it bloody well is now.      - Hugh, don't.
该死的你和你那没用的机器
Damn you and your useless machine.
我的机器是我们获胜的关键
My machine is how we are going to win.
是吗？
Really?
这台机器吗？嗯？
This machine? Hmm?
你是说这该死的机器？！
Are you talking about this bloody machine?!
-休！休！休，不要！             -休！休！住手！
- Hugh! Hugh! Hugh, don't!      - Hugh! Hugh! Stop!
你这个傲慢的混蛋
You arrogant bastard.
你本可以帮助我们
You could help us.
你可以让运算更快，但是你没有
You could make this go faster, but you won't.
松手
Get off.
他是对的，艾伦
He's right, Alan.
在外面有...
There are...
有真正的战士在保家卫国
actual soldiers out there trying to win an actual war.
我的兄弟
My brother
在海军的护卫食品车队里
protects food convoys in the Navy.
我的表兄弟在皇家空军巡逻
My cousins fly RAF patrols.
我所有的朋友，他们都在改变
All my friends,they're all making a difference,
而我们只是……虚度光阴
while we just...while away our days
做无用功
producing nothing.
这一切都因为你
Because of you.
我的机器…
My machine...
会有用的
will work.
走吧，彼得
Come on, Peter.
你可以走了
Okay
琼？
Joan?
哦
Oh.
呃，你能不能...
Uh, will you...
你可不可以
Could you make
再大声点？我怕我的
a bit more noise? I'm not quite sure
- 房东没被吵醒                  - 哦，不好意思
- my landlady woke up.          - Oh, sorry.
噢，嗯，听着
Oh, uh, look.
我想这是尽最大努力能做的了
I think that's the best I can do.
天黑之后不允许有男性访客
No male visitors after dark.
那么…
So...
你给我带来什么？
what did you bring me?
开始吧
There you go.
给你
Here.
你知道其他男人会送花吧
Some men try flowers, you know.
这些都是真正的英格玛信息
These are actual decrypted Enigma messages
直接从纳粹截获的
direct from Nazi
最高命令
High Command.
“0600个小时
"0600 hours.
“今天白天天气晴朗
"Weather today is clear.
“晚上有雨
"Rain in the evening.
希特勒万岁”
Heil Hitler."
嗯，很明显，这个重要的信息
Well, clearly,that vital piece of information
会帮助我们赢得战争
is going to win us the war.
我感兴趣的正是加密
It's the relationship between the encrypted
和解密的信息
a-and decrypted messages that interests me.
我们可以找找线索，好构建到克里斯托弗中去？
Can we find a clue here that we can build into Christopher?
谁是克里斯托弗？
Who's Christopher?
哦，他，呃，他是我的机器
Oh, he's, uh,he's my machine.
你给他命名了？
You named him?
名字很糟糕吗？
Is that a bad name?
不
No.
不是，不管它了
No, never mind.
你是想建立你的通用机器？
Are you trying to build your universal machine?
我读过你的文章
I read your paper
- 在大学          -已经开这门课了？
- at university.  - Is it already being taught?
不，没有，我只是提前看看
No. No. No, I was precocious.
所以…
So...
你的理论上说有一个机器
you-you theorized a machine that
能解决任何问题
could solve any problem.
它不仅会做一件事，而是什么都会
It didn't just do one thing,it did everything.
不仅仅是可编程的，而且还能可重复编程
It wasn't just programmable,it was reprogrammable.
嗯
Mm.
克里斯托弗背后就是你的这个理论吧？
Is that your idea behind Christopher?
嗯，人类的大脑可以很快计算大量的数据…
Well, human brains can compute large sums very quickly...
即使是休都能做到…但我想克里斯托弗更聪明
even Hugh can do that... but I want Christopher to be smarter.
做一个计算，然后，呃…
To make a calculation and then, uh...
来决定下一步该做什么
to determine what to do next.
就像一个真正的人那样做
Like a person does.
想想看
Think of it.
电子大脑
Electrical brain.
数字计算机
A digital computer.
Digital computer.
嗯
Hmm.
怎么了？
What's going on?
发生什么事了？
What's happening?
不，不，不，不！别碰那个！
No. No, no. No, no, no!Don't touch that!
-退后              -这是我的桌子
- Stay back.       - That's my desk.
谢天谢地
Thank goodness.
我不想我们找了半天
I'd hate to think we were searching
- 却都是错误的        - 你在做什么？倒底发生什么事了？
- the wrong one.    - What are you doing? What's going on?
有一个间谍
There is a spy
在布莱奇利园
in Bletchley Park.
海军认为我们中的一个
The Navy thinks that one of us
是苏联双重间谍，艾伦
is a Soviet double agent, Alan.
呃……为什么？
Uh...why?
我们在它被送往莫斯科途中截获了这个
Our boys intercepted this on its way to Moscow.
看起来眼熟吗？
Look familiar?
这是比尔密码
It's a Beale cipher.
加密来自一本书中的一个短语或一首诗或…
Encrypted with a phrase from a book or a poem or...
你不会认为这是我做的吧？
You don't seriously think I did this, do you?
双面特工是个混蛋
Double agents are such bastards.
孤立者
Isolated loners.
没有朋友或家人
No attachments to friends or family.
傲慢
Arrogant.
认识这样的人吗？
Know anybody like that?
我知道你不喜欢我
Hm, I know you don't like me,
但这并不意味我是
but that does not make me
苏联间谍
a Soviet spy.
没找到什么，先生
Nothing out of the ordinary, sir.
是嘛
Really.
嗯，好吧
Mm, all right.
虽然内政部现在可以保护你
The Home Office may be protecting you now,
但迟早
but sooner or later
你会犯错
you will make a mistake.
我不必费心解雇你
And I needn't bother firing you.
他们会以叛国罪绞死你
They will hang you for treason.
嗨
Hello.
我知道今天的事了
I heard about what happened.
这是三组女孩唯一可以谈论的事
It's all the girls in Hut 3 can talk about.
我有个主意可以让你振作起来
I have an idea of what might cheer you up.
因为没有字母
So because no letter
可以自身编码，已经有少数
can be encoded as itself,there's already a handful
设定打一开始就被拒绝
of settings that can be rejected at the outset.
那是你的团队？
Is that your team?
- 是的      -我们要打招呼吗？
- Y-Yes.    - Shall we say hello?
- 不要         - 嗨
- No.          - Hello.
我说过不要打招呼
L-I told you not to do that.
- 艾伦         -呃，休，嗨
- Alan.        - Uh, Hugh, h-hello.
-我不知道你会喝酒            - 他不喝
- Didn't know you drank.      - He doesn't, really.
他只是喝一点泡沫
He just sort of sips at the foam.
好吧，我告诉你个小秘密，小姐..
Well, I'll let you into a little secret, Miss...?
叫我克拉克
Clarke.
- 克拉克小姐            -请讲
- Miss Clarke.          - Please.
泡沫也是我最喜欢的部分
Foam's my favorite part, too.
这是真的吗？
Is it really?
来和我们一起喝一杯吧？
Come and join us for a drink?
我们一会儿就过来
We'll be there in a moment.
克拉克小姐
Miss Clarke.
嗯，他喜欢你
Well, he likes you.
-是的        -你…
- Yes.       -You...
故意让他喜欢你
g-got him to like you.
是的
Yes.
为什么？
Why?
因为我做的是男人们的工作
Because I'm a woman in a man's job,
而且我有没有可以引以为傲的本事
and I don't have the luxury of being an ass.
艾伦…
Alan...
不管你有多聪明
it doesn't matter how smart you are,
英格玛永远比你聪明
Enigma is always smarter.
如果你真的
If you really
要解决你的难题
want to solve your puzzle,
那么你要利用你可以得到的
then you're going to need all the help
所有帮助，他们是不会
you can get,and they are not going
来帮助你，如果他们不喜欢你的话
to help you if they do not like you.
-那是什么？             -苹果
- What are those?       - Apples.
-不会吧           -哦，还真是
- No.             - Oh, they really are.
呃，我..嗯，克拉克小姐，我叫她琼，嗯…
Um, l... well, Miss Clarke,Joan actually, um...
她说这样会
said that it would be...
很不错，额，如果我给你们带些东西的话
Nice if I was to, uh,bring you all something.
所以我就这么做了，我...
So here we are. I...
谢谢
Thank you.
我喜欢苹果
I like apples.
替我向克拉克小姐问好
My best to Miss Clarke.
额，树林中的两个人
Uh, there are two people in a wood,
呃，他们碰到一只熊
and, um, they run into a bear.
第一个人跪下祈祷
The first person gets down on his knees to pray.
第二个人开始绑紧他的鞋带
The second person starts lacing up his boots.
第一个人问第二个人
The first person asks the second person,
“我亲爱的朋友，你在做什么？
"My dear friend,what are you doing?
你-你-你跑不过熊的”
You-you-you can't outrun a bear."
呃，第二个人说
Uh, to which the second person responds,
“我不需要跑过熊
"I don't have to.
我只需跑过你就行”
I only have to outrun you."
我会在克里斯托弗那，如果有人需要我的话
I'll be w-with Christopher, if anyone needs me.
如果我们假设2的平方根
If we assume that the square root of two
是个有理数，那么可以说
is a rational number,then we can say
2的平方根
that the square root of two
是A/B
is A over B...
其中A和B
where A and B
是整数，B不能为零
are whole numbers and B is not zero.
图灵先生，你在传纸条吗？
Mr. Turing,passing notes, are we?
没有，先生
No, sir.
只有图灵会传写着胡言乱语的纸条
Only Turing would pass notes written in gibberish.
好了，先生们
All right, gentlemen,
假期别忘了你们的代数
do not forget your algebra over the break.
假期愉快，当你们回来的
Have a pleasant holiday,and we'll resume
时候我们开始讲无理数
your irrationals when you return.
嗯
Mm.
用欧拉定理就可以直接算出答案
But Euler's Theorem gives you that immediately.
嗯...
Um...
给你，你看下这个
Here. Look at this.
如果你运行的电线穿过插板矩阵的对角
If you run the wires across the plugboard matrix diagonally,
这将使转子位置的消除速度达到500倍
it will eliminate rotor positions 500 times faster.
这个，呃...
That's, uh...
其实不完全是一个糟糕的主意
actually not an entirely terrible idea.
我想艾伦是在说“谢谢”
I think that was Alan for "thank you."
呃，那是我的三明治
Uh, th-that's my sandwich.
你不喜欢三明治
You don't like sandwiches.
你紧张吗？
You nervous?
现在它在干嘛？
What happens now?
它应该能算出英格玛的设定
It-it should work out the day's Enigma settings.
需要多久？
How long?
胜利万岁！胜利万岁！
Sieg Heil! Sieg Heil!
德国军队已经遍布欧洲
The German Army has fanned out across Europe,
从波兰到塞尔维亚，立陶宛到丹麦
from Poland to Serbia,Lithuania to Denmark,
挪威到法国
Norway to France.
纳粹国旗已插在二十多个
The Nazi flag now flies from more than two dozen
国家的首都
national capitals.
他们来势凶猛
Their campaign mounts in fury
想使自由的欧洲崩溃
as a free Europe crumbles.
哦，它还在运行中
Oh, it's still going.
- 早上好，先生          -早上好，玛格丽特
- Good morning, sir.    - Morning, Margaret.
齿轮一直转
Gears keep spinning on and on.
转子也一直在动
Rotors on and on.
没有停过
It's endless.
还不能看出什么结果吗？
With no result in sight?
不能
No.
哇
Ow.
图灵
Turing.
Turing,
-打开这该死的门                  - 哦，不
- open the bloody door.          - Uh, no.
不开
No.
开门不然我们就强行进入了
Open the door or we'll break it down.
我不能让你进来！我. ..我不能让你干涉
I can't let you in! I-l...I cannot let you interfere.
踹开它
Go on, then.
把那东西关掉
Turn that thing off.
不，不要，求你了，别这样
No. Don't, please. Please.
不要！求求你！
Please! Please!
不！
No!
别，别关！
N-No. No!
不要!
Don't!
嗯，那么，看来你伟大的大型
Well, then, it seems that your great big
贵重机器没什么用处啊
expensive machine doesn't work.
有用
It does.
很好
Wonderful.
也就是说你破解了英格玛了？
So you've broken Enigma, then?
只是...
It was just...
还在运算中
s-still working.
这是我在内政部的同事
This is my associate from the Home Office.
你知道，十万英镑
You see, a hundred thousand pounds
可不是什么小钱
is rather a lot of money,
他过来看是想知道有什么结果
and he's here to see what you have to show for it.
你…永远都不会懂
You... will never understand
我在这所做的事情的重要性！
the importance of what I-l am creating here!
你有解密德国的任何消息吗？
Have you decrypted any German messages?
哪怕一条也行？
A single one?
你能说说你完成了什么吗？
Can you point to anything at all that you've achieved?
嗯，你的资金用完了
Hmm. Your funding is up,
我们的耐心是有限度的
and our patience is expired.
真是开心
It's with such great pleasure
能说出这句话
that I am finally able to say this.
艾伦图灵，你被解雇了
Alan Turing,you're fired.
请送图灵先生离开这里
Please escort Mr. Turing from the premises.
不可以
No.
你说什么？
I beg your pardon?
如果你解雇艾伦…
If you fire Alan...
那，把我也解雇了吧
well, then you'll have to fire me, too.
你知道你在说什么吗？
What on earth are you saying?
相信我没有人比我跟
Trust me when I tell you there is no one
不想承认我所说的，但是…
who would rather say this less than I do, but...
他是对的
he's right.
艾伦是对的
Alan is right.
他的机器可以运作，它可能是
His machine can work,and it's probably
我们所拥有的最好的机会
the best chance that we've got.
天啊，真是难以置信
God, it's beyond belief.
如果你解雇他们…
If you fire them...
那你也得解雇我
you'll have to fire me, too.
还有我
And me.
我们是英国最好的解密学家
We're the best cryptographic minds in Britain.
你要解雇我们所有人吗？
Are you going to fire us all?
指挥官，至少给我们一些时间
Commander, at least give us some more time
六个月，如果机器不产生
Six months, and if the machine doesn't produce
任何我们需要的结果，然后我们就重新
any results that we need,then we'll go back
使用以前的方法……怎么样？
to doing things the old way...how about that?
一个月
One month.
如果你们都走的话
And then,so help me God,
那可不得了
you're all gone.
哦，放开他
Oh, leave him.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不用客气
You're welcome.
哦，艾伦，你的机器...
Oh, and, Alan,your machine...
...最好该死的有用
...it better bloody work.
休
Hugh.
我发誓…
I swear...
我不是间谍
I'm not a spy.
哦，天啊，你当然不是一个该死的间谍
Oh, for God's sake, of course you're not a bloody spy.
什么？
What?
丹尼斯顿给我比尔密码
Denniston gave me the Beale cipher,
你猜怎么着？
and guess what?
我破解了它
I cracked it.
“求，就会给予汝
"Ask, and it shall be given to you;
寻，就能寻见”马太福音第七章第七段
seek and ye shall find." Matthew 7:7.
这就是关键所在
That was the key.
对像你这样的人来说太简单了
Far too simple for the likes of you.
可怜的丹尼斯顿不同意
Pity Denniston disagrees.
进来
Come in.
先生，我觉得我发现图灵的证据了
Sir, I think I've got Turing.
我昨晚跟踪他
I tailed him
到一个酒吧，在那里他遇到了一个家伙
to a pub last night,where he met a bloke.
他们交换了一个信封
They exchanged an envelope.
所以我跟着这个家伙
So I follow this other fella,
抓了他，好好的审问了下
pick him up,give him a good shake.
他说他是一个同性恋，他招了一切，
He's a poofter.He confessed.
什么？
What?
他说他叫阿诺德莫里
The man admitted it.Arnold Murray.
在酒吧附近闲逛，等男人买他一夜春宵
Hangs around that pub;men pay him for a go.
图灵就是其中一个
Turing's one of the men that paid.
这个莫里先生
Only Mr. Murray here
在事后和他的朋友
then has the bright idea
想到一个聪明的主意一同去打劫图灵的房子
of robbing Turing's house after, with a friend.
这就是图灵所隐藏的秘密
That's what Turing's hiding.
好吧，他是个同性恋，不是间谍
Well, he's a poof, not a spy.
- 不    -怎么了？
- No.   - What's the matter?
我们可以控告一个大学教授
We can charge a university professor
- 猥亵             - 不，这简直..
- with indecency.   - No, this is...
没有任何意义
it's bloody rubbish.
图灵企图做一些更重要的事情…
Turing's up to something important...
他犯了罪，并且做了违法的事
He's committed a crime and he's broken the law.
和男人上床，天啊
And with a bloke.Jesus Christ,
- 这真让人恶心              -这不是
- it's bloody disgusting.   - This isn't
我正在进行调查的事情
the investigation I was conducting.
把他带来
Bring him in.
等下
Wait.
让我来审问他
L-Let me interrogate him.
给我单独半个小时就行
Please. Give me half an hour alone,
我发誓，下个月
and then I swear,I'll spend the next month
你给我的任何烂案子我都接
running errands on as many rubbish cases as you like.
好吧，现在，谁给我弄个抓
Fine. Now,will someone get me a warrant
艾伦 图灵逮捕令
for the arrest of Alan Turing.
艾伦？
Alan?
克里斯托弗实在太慢了
Christopher's simply not moving fast enough.
- 我们应该谈谈      -即使有捷径
- We should talk.   - And even with the diagonal board,
他还是不能快速消除设定
he's still not eliminating settings as quickly
- 我们需要他让...                 - 我要走了
- as we need him to in order...   - I'm leaving.
但你才刚来
But you've just walked in.
不
No.
不是的，是离开布莱奇利
No. Bletchley.
怎么了？
What?
是我的父母
It's my parents.
我25岁，未婚，独自生活
I'm 25, I'm unmarried,I'm living alone,
他们想让我回家
and they want me home.
这太荒谬了
That's ridiculous.
这就是我的父母
That's my parents.
你... 你不能离开...我不会让你走的
You... you can't leave...l-l won't let you.
“我会想你的”这是一个平常人
"I'll miss you." That's what a normal person
- 在这种情况下都会说的话         - 我不关心平常不平常
- might say in this situation.   - I-l don't care what is normal.
我该做
What am I supposed
些什么，艾伦？
to do, Alan?
我..我是不会...
L-I will not...
抛弃我的父母的
give up my parents.
你...你在这里有机会
You... you have an opportunity here
去实现你的自身价值
to make some actual use of your life.
然后你一样的下场？不，谢谢
And end up like you?No, thanks.
我为你的孤独感到难过
I'm sorry you're lonely.
英格玛也救不了你
But Enigma will not save you.
你能破解它吗？你个脆弱的自恋狂
Can you decipher that,you fragile narcissist?
还是你想让我去找你的
Or would you like me to go and fetch
宝贝克里斯托弗来帮忙？
your precious Christopher to help?
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
嗯..
Mm...
我想你…我想你留下来因为我喜欢你
I want you... I want you to stay because I-l like you.
我喜欢和你…说话
I like...talking to you.
我也喜欢和你说话，艾伦
I like talking to you,too, Alan.
如果你不再是一个人？
And what if you weren't alone?
如果你有一个丈夫呢？
What if you had a husband?
你有理想的人选吗？
Do you have one in mind?
我有
I do.
休？
Hugh?
休很有魅力，我承认
Hugh's terribly attractive,I'll give you that,
但他不是我想结婚的那种
but I don't really think he's the marrying kind.
不，我没有在想休
No, I-l wasn't thinking of Hugh.
那就是彼得
Or Peter.
彼得太安静了
Peter's so quiet.
哦，我的天啊
Oh, my God.
但是这是合乎情理的
But this makes sense.
你是在向我求婚吗？
Did you just propose to me?
嗯，这是顺理成章的事
Well, it is the logical thing to do.
- 这太荒谬了                 - 这是你的父母想要的
- This is ridiculous.        - This is your parents.
我-我不信..居然就这么发生了
I-I can't... believe that this is happening.
呃，琼…
Mm. Joan...
你的中间名是卡洛琳还是凯瑟琳？
Is your middle name Caroline or Catherine?
-伊丽莎白            -嗯，琼 伊丽莎白…
- Elizabeth.         - Um, Joan Elizabeth...
克拉克，嗯…
Clarke, um...
...你愿意嫁给我吗？
...will you marry me?
太漂亮了
It's beautiful.
嗯，我知道这不常见，不过…
Well, I know it isn't ordinary, but...
喜欢常见的呢？
whoever loved ordinary?
她把它捧在手上...
She had it in both hands...
然后她抬头看着我说，
And she looked up at me with her doe eyes and said,
“我应该把它放进我的嘴里吗？”
"Am I supposed to put that in my mouth?"
我说，“是的，你知道的，像法国人那样”
And I said, "Yes.You know, the French way."
然后她把它放进嘴里
So she pops it in,
把它含住
clamps her lips around it,
并开始哼唱那该死的马赛曲
and starts humming the bloody Marseillaise.
我们跳舞吧
Come have a dance.
不，不，不，你可以在任何时间
No, no,no, you can dance
和你的未婚夫跳舞
with your fiance anytime you like.
现在，这一刻…
Right now, this moment...
轮到我了
my turn.
怎么了？
What's the matter?
要是...
Wh-What if...
要是我不喜欢...
Wh-What if I don't fancy being...
和琼那样怎么办？
with Joan I-in that way?
因为你是同性恋？
Because you're a homosexual?
我怀疑过
I suspected.
嗯，我该不该告诉她
Well, should-should I tell her
我和
that I've had...
男人发生过关系？
affairs with men?
你知道，以我...
You know, in my...
有限的经验看来
admittedly limited experience,
女人…往往是有点敏感关于
women... tend to be a bit touchy
不小心嫁给同性恋
about accidentally marrying homosexuals.
也许不要把这个消息传开
Perhaps not spreading this information about might be
对你来说最好
in your best interest.
我在乎她
I care for her,
真的，我...
I truly do. I...
我..我只是不知道
I-I... I just don't know
我是否可以，呃，继续装下去
if I can, um... pretend.
你不能告诉任何人，艾伦
You can't tell anyone, Alan.
这是违法的
It's illegal.
丹尼斯顿可以找任何借口
And Denniston is looking for any excuse he can
把你带走
to put you away.
我知道
I know.
保守这个秘密
This has to stay a secret.
来吧，轮到你了
Come on, it's your turn.
啊，好的
Ah. Okay.
要茶吗？
Cup of tea?
不，谢谢
No, thank you.
图灵先生，我可以告诉你一个秘密吗？
Mr. Turing, can I tell you a secret?
秘密我很在行
I'm quite good with those.
我是来帮你的
I'm here to help you.
哦，显而易见
Oh, clearly.
机器能思考吗？
Can machines think?
哦，所以你看过我的作品咯？
Oh, so you've read some of my published works?
你为什么这么说？
What makes you say that?
嗯，因为我坐在警察局，
Well, because I'm sitting in a police station,
被指控要求一个年轻男子摸我的阴茎
accused of entreating a young man to touch my penis
而你只是问我机器能思考吗？
and you just asked me if machines can think.
那么，它们能吗？
Well, can they?
机器能像人类一样思考吗？
Could machines ever think as human beings do?
大多数人说不能
Most people say not.
你不是大多数人
You're not most people.
嗯，问题在于你...问了个傻问题
Well, the problem is you're...asking a stupid question.
是吗？
I am?
机器当然...
Of course machines...
不能像人类一样思考
can't think as people do.
机器和人是不同的
A machine is different...from a person.
因此，他们思考的方式也不同
Hence, they think differently.
有趣的是，仅仅因为某些，嗯
The interesting question is,just because something, uh,
思考方式与你不同
thinks differently from you,
是不是就意味着他们没有思考能力？
does that mean it's not thinking?
嗯，我们人类之间就有
Well, we allow for humans to have such divergences
这样的不同
from one another.
你喜欢吃草莓，我恨滑冰
You like strawberries,I hate ice-skating,
你...会为悲伤的电影哭泣
you... cry at sad films,
我..我对花粉过敏
I... am allergic to pollen.
不同口味的不同点是什么
What is the point of-of different tastes,
不同的…偏好的不同点又是什么
different... preferences
如果不是说我们的大脑工作方式不同
if not to say that our brains work differently,
我们怎会想的不一样呢？
that we think differently?
如果我们可以这样认为人的思考方式
And if we can say that about one another,
那为什么不能这么认为由
then why can't we say the same thing for brains...
铜和电缆构成的大脑也有思考能力？
built of copper and wire, steel?
这就是...
And that's...
你写的文章？
this big paper you wrote?
名字叫什么
What's it called?
“模仿游戏”
"The Imitation Game."
好的，那..
Right, that's...
那它是关于什么的？
that's what it's about?
你想玩吗？
Would you like to play?
玩？
Play?
这是一个游戏
It's a game.
一种测试
A test of sorts.
用于确定某物是...
For determining whether something is a...
机器还是人
a machine or a human being.
怎么玩？
How do I play?
嗯，有一个法官和一个测试对象，呃...
Well, there's a judge and a subject, and...
法官问问题
the judge asks questions,
根据测试对象给出的答案
and, depending on the subject's answers,
来判断法官是在和谁...
determines who he is talking with...
或者和某物说话…
what he is talking with,and, um...
你所需要做的是问我一个问题
All you have to do is ask me a question.
战争期间你在做什么？
What did you do during the war?
我在一个无线电工厂工作
I worked in a radio factory.
在战争期间你真正在做的是什么？
What did you really do during the war?
你有注意听我说话吗？
Are you paying attention?
该死的！
Damn it!
我们快没时间了，就一个月
We're soon out of time. A month.
所以就这样了，是吗？
So that's it, then, is it?
哦，问题是，不管我们如何改善它
Oh, the trouble is, it doesn't matter how much we improve it.
机器还是不可能解决
The machine's never gonna be able to process
159百万亿的可能性
159 million million million possibilities in time.
没希望了
It's just bloody hopeless.
它在搜寻，只是..
It's searching.It's just...
不知道它在搜寻什么
It... doesn't know what it's searching for.
如果我们知道这个消息要表达的是什么…
If we knew what the messages were going to say...
如果我们知道这个消息要表达的是什么
If we knew what the messages were going to say,
我们就不需要破解它
we wouldn't have to decrypt them at all.
艾伦的那个朋友是谁？
Who's Alan's friend?
休，他其实有点下流
Hugh. He's a bit of a cad, actually.
很好，是我的类型
So my type, then?
- 好吧，我给你介绍一下              -不要
- Well, I'll introduce you.         - No.
他会过来的
He'll come over.
-你确定？            -确定
- Are you sure?      - Yes.
我15分钟前对他笑了一下
I smiled at him 15 minutes ago
然后就没看其他地方了
and haven't looked back since.
琼旁边的是谁？
Who's that with Joan?
嗯？
Hmm?
呃，海伦，她的同事
Uh, Helen. Works with her.
她真漂亮
She's really pretty.
她希望我过去
She wants me to come over.
什么？你怎么知道？
What? H-How on earth can you know that?
她对我笑了笑
She smiled at me a while back
然后就没看其他地方了
and she hasn't looked again since.
他上钩了
And got him.
现在，这是为什么，当我是单身时
Now, why is this,that when I was single
我发现这很无聊，但现在我订婚了
I found it very boring,but now that I'm engaged,
我却觉得这很有趣
I just find it dreadfully fun.
宾戈，她上钩了
Bingo. She's in.
艾伦，给我们引介一下
Alan, introduce us.
什么？为什么是我？
What? Wh-Why me?
因为没有什么能像一个朋友的订婚
Because there's nothing like a friend's engagement
使一个女人想要和她朋友的未婚夫的帅气朋友
to make a woman want to do something she'll later regret
做点她事后会后悔的事
with the fiance's better looking chum.
我们过去
Let's go.
半克朗赌艾伦会搞砸
Half a crown says Alan bollixes this up entirely.
不赌
No bet.
- 艾伦图灵有个理论                - 他有很多
- Alan Turing has a theory.       -  He has many.
他认为禁止男人与女人
He believes that the regulations
一起工作的规定是正确的
against men and women working side by side are sound
因为这样的接近必然导致情愫
because such proximity will necessarily lead to romance.
什么？不，我没有，我...
What? No,I don't. I...
然而…
However...
我不同意
I disagree.
-是吗？        -是的
- You do?      - Yeah.
我想如果我整天和一个女人一起工作
I think that if I were working beside a woman all daylong,
不用和她上床
I could appreciate her abilities and intellect
就能欣赏她的能力和智慧很好
without taking her to bed.
对不起，我们见过吗？
I'm sorry, have we met?
我不记得，但我觉得我们没有
I don't recall.But let's assume we haven't.
海伦 斯图尔特，休 亚力山大
Helen Stewart.Hugh Alexander.
那你赞成谁的
So who do you agree with,
-艾伦还是我的？       -当然是艾伦的
- Alan or myself?     - Well, Alan, of course.
我很高兴，真的，但我不认为…
L-I'm very flattered, really,but I-l don't think...
-  胡说           - 我每天都和男人
-  Rubbish.        - Well, I work beside a man
一起工作，我控制不住
every day,and I can't help
不让自己对他产生点感觉
but have developed a bit of a crush on him.
嗯，这个人是谁？我要揍他一顿
Well, who is this man?So I can kick his arse.
好的，不用担心…只是想想而已
Well, there's no need to worry... it's been chaste.
我们甚至都没见过，他是个德国人
We've never even met.He's a German.
现在我真想杀了他
Now I really want to kill him.
你说德国人一起工作是什么意思？
How-how do you mean you work alongside a German?
嗯，我们每个人都从一个特定的
Well, each of us intercepts messages
德国广播塔拦截信息
from a specific German radio tower.
所以我们在另一边有个同行
So we have a counterpart on the other side
再打这些信息
who's tip-tapping out the messages.
每个人都有不同的节奏
Everyone types a touch differently,
所以你会开始了解你的同行的节奏
so you get to know the rhythm of your counterpart.
有种奇怪的亲密感
It's strangely intimate.
我觉得我很了解他
I feel as if I know him so well.
可惜他有女朋友
It's a pity he has a girlfriend,
这就是为什么我不同意你的观点，亚力山大先生
but that's why I disagree  with you, Mr. Alexander.
因为我爱上了一个同事
Because I'm in love with a coworker of sorts,
我们甚至都没见过面
and we've never even met.
好的，请允许我给你买一杯酒
Well, allow me to buy you another pint,
然后我会告诉你为什么你错了
and I'll tell you why you're wrong.
好的
Let's.
太好了
Excellent.
谢谢
Thanks.
啤酒，你们有松子酒吗？
Um, pints.Have you got any sloe gin?
以防你不知道那行为就是调情
In case you were wondering,that's what flirting looks like.
海伦…
Helen...
-真的没有香烟吗？            -艾伦…
- Really, no cigarettes?      - Alan...
怎么了艾伦？
Yes, Alan?
为什么你认为
Wh-Why do you think
你的德国同行有一个女朋友？
your German counterpart has a girlfriend?
-只是一个愚蠢的笑话；别在意               - 不，不，不，不行，告诉我
- It's just a stupid joke; don't worry.   - No, no, no, no. Tell me.
嗯，他的每一个信息
Well, each of his messages
都用相同的五个字母开头：
begins with the same five letters:
C-I-L-L-Y
C-I-L-L-Y.
所以我猜想希里可能就是他
So I suspect that Cilly must be the name
- 女友的名字       -但那是不可能的
- of his amore.    - But that's impossible.
德国人指示使用五个随机字母
The Germans are instructed to use five random letters
为每一个信息的开头
at the start of every message.
好吧，这小子不是
Well, this bloke doesn't.
我认为爱情会使人做奇怪的事
Love will make a man do strange things, I suppose.
那在这种情况下，德国将输给爱情一场战争
In this case, love just lost Germany the whole bloody war.
哦1
Oh!
走，彼得
Go, Peter.
不好意思
Sorry.
艾伦！艾伦1
Alan! Alan!
喔，喔，喔，喔!嘿，等下！
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!Hey, hey, hey!
艾伦！
Alan!
我只是....
I just want...
休 亚力山大，约翰 凯恩克罗斯
Hugh Alexander.John Cairncross.
彼得该死的希尔顿
Peter bloody Hilton.
艾伦？怎-怎么了？
Alan? What-wha…?
如果
What...
如果克里斯托弗
what if...what if Christopher
不用搜寻所有的设定
doesn't have to search through all of the settings?
如果他只需要检查几个词
What if he only has to search through
在情报里我们已经知道的
ones that produce words we already know will be
- 是什么？             -重复可以预见的词
- in the message?      - Repeated words; predictable words.
没错
Exactly.
看，看，比如这个
Look, look, like this one.
“0600小时，今天白天天气晴朗
"0600 hours. Weather today is clear.
“晚上有雨，希特勒万岁”
Rain in the evening. Heil Hitler."
这就是了
Well, that's it.
没错
Exactly.
他们每天六点发一份天气预报
They send a weather report every day at 6:00 a.m.
所以我-我们已经知道
So that's-that's three words we know will be
在每天六点的情报中有“天气”这个词，绝对的
in every 6:00 a.m. message..."weather," obviously,
- 还有..          -该死的希特勒万岁
- a-and...        - Heil bloody Hitler.
该死的希特勒万岁
Heil bloody Hitler.
这是今天早上六点的信息
Here's the 6:00 message from this morning.
休，呃
Hugh, the, uh,
坐标字母轮子设定它为
the right-hand letter wheel,set them to...
我知道，我知道，“天气”和“希特勒”
I know, I know."Weather" and "Hitler."
彼得，约翰，运行电子扰频器给
Peter, John, run voltages through those letters,
-这些字母通电压                  -所以我们用线圈是吗？
- through the back scramblers.   - So we'll use the loops?
是的，琼，早上六点最后的情报是什么？
Yes. Joan, what was the last 6:00 a.m. message?
- L...        - L...
H...
- H...         -W...
W...
-  A...     - A...
- Q.        -Q.
完成
Done.
快点
Come on.
快点，快点，克里斯托弗
Come on.Come on, Christopher.
哦，天啊
Oh, my God.
怎么了？
Wh-What happened?
- 有用吗？              - 艾伦？
- Did it work?           - Alan?
艾伦！艾伦！
Alan! Alan!
我需要一份新信息
I need a new message.
最新的情报密码
The latest intercept.
谢谢
Thank you.
O... T...
-好了吗？   -可以了
- Ready?    - Yes.
- M...       - M...
- Y...        -Y...
- M... S...     - M... S...
- A... I...       -A... I...
- C...          -C...
- T...          -T...
- R...          - R...
- S... O...           -S... O...
- A...                -A...
- Y... R... I...          -Y... R...
I
I.
“KMS捷豹被指示去
"KMS Jaguar is auf punkt...
“北纬五十三度二十四分
"is directed to 53 degrees 24 minutes north
西边一度的...海域
and auf punkt one...degree west."
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler.
原来是你唯一需要知道的是一个德国单词
Turns out that's the only German you need to know
就能破解英格玛
to, uh, break Enigma.
太棒了
Yes!
哦！
Oh!
-  M...         - M...
- A...               -A...
- Y...              -Y...
- T...            -T...
- R...             - R...
- O...      -O... T...
- T...A...        -A...
- H...          - H...
- Q...           -Q...
-  U...            - U...
- R.             -R.
天啊!你做到了
My God, you did it.
你只用了猜字游戏就赢了纳粹
You just defeated Nazism with a crossword puzzle.
这世界上只有五个人
There are five people in the world who know
知道所有在大西洋的潜艇的位置
the position of every ship in the Atlantic.
他们都在
They're all
- 这个房间里            - 我的天啊
- in this room.         - Oh, good God.
哦，我认为上帝都做不到我们
Oh, I don't think even He has the power
- 所做到的                      - 不是
- that we do right now.         -No.
这将会有一个对英国客船
There's going to be an attack
护航的突袭
on a British passenger convoy.
在这里
Right there.
天啊，你是对的，所有潜艇距离只有
God, you're right. All those U-boats are only
- 二、三十分钟的时间          - 普通百姓
- 20, 3O minutes away.        - Civilians.
成千上百的普通百姓，我们可以救他们
Hundreds of them. We can save their lives.
我们可以给丹尼斯顿办公室打电话
I'll phone Denniston's office so that
- 这样他就可以提醒下海军部          - 你觉得
- he can alert the Admiralty.       - Do you think
有足够的时间救他们吗
there's enough time to save them?
应该有吧，如果我们能及时接通
There should be,if we can get...
指挥官丹尼斯顿的办公室的话，请快点，这是紧急的
Commander Denniston's office,please. It's urgent.
不
No.
你到底在干什么
What the hell are you doing?
你不能打给丹尼斯顿
You-you can't call Denniston.
你- 你不能告诉他关于突袭的事
You-you can't tell him about the attack.
-你在说什么？                   - 我们可以
- What are you talking about?   - We can have
在十分钟之能给护航空中支援
air support over that convoy in ten minutes.
让潜艇...
Let the U-boats...
-打沉护航                  - 听着，我们知道
- sink the convoy.         - Look, it's been
你工作了很久 ...也许你...
a big day...maybe you're...
-我们没有时间...               - 不！
- We don't have time...        - No!
哦!休！休！可以了！
Oh! Hugh! Hugh!That's enough!
- 你够了！              - 住手，休！
- That's enough!        - Stop, Hugh!
约翰，这个突袭在分秒之间
John, the attack is in minutes.
不用，我没事，我很好
Yes, no, I'm fine, I'm fine.
我没事
I'm fine.
你知道为什么人们喜欢暴力吗？休
You know why people like violence, Hugh?
因为它使人感觉很好
It's because it feels good.
有时我们不能做什么的感觉很好的事
Sometimes we can't do what feels good.
我们要做的是理智的事
We have to do what is logical.
什么理智的事？
What's logical?
最难的欺骗是
Hardest time to lie to somebody
当他们有防备被骗的时候
is when they're expecting to be lied to.
哦，天啊
Oh, God.
怎么了？
What?
当有人正在等待着一个谎言时
If someone's waiting for a lie,
你不能，呃，给他们一个
you can't just,uh, give them one.
该死的，艾伦是对的
Damn it, Alan's right.
什么？
What?
如果我们摧毁了他们的潜艇
What would the Germans think if we destroy
德军会怎么想？
their U-boats?
还能怎么想，他们都死了
Nothing. They'll be dead.
不
No.
不，你不可能是对的
No, you can't be right.
我们的护航队伍
So our convoy
突然偏离路线…
suddenly veers off course...
一群空军轰炸机
a squadron of our air bombers
奇迹般地降落在德国潜艇的坐标上…
miraculously descends on the coordinates of the U-boats...
德军会怎么想？
what will the Germans think?
德军会知道
The Germans will know
我们破解了英格玛
that we have broken Enigma.
他们会在中午停止一切无线电通信
They'll stop all radio communications by midday,
在这个周末改变英格玛的
and they'll have changed the design of Enigma
- 设定                       - 没错
- by the weekend.            -  Yes.
两年的工作
Two years' work.
我们所做的这一切
Everything that we've done here
都将白费
will all be for nothing.
在那艘护航上有五百个普通百姓
There are 500 civilians in that convoy.
女人...
Women...
孩子
children.
我们是在送他们去死
We're about to let them die.
我们的工作不是
Our job I-is
去就一艘护航船，而是去赢得
not to save one passenger convoy, it is to win
-战争               - 我们的工作是破解英格玛
- the war.          - Our job was to crack Enigma.
我们做到了了
We've done that.
现在是最困难的部分
Now for the hard part.
- 保守秘密              -卡莱尔
- Keeping it a secret.  - Carlisle.
什么？
What?
这个你说的护航船...它，呃
The convoy you're about to...it's, uh...
是皇家公务船中的其中一艘，叫卡莱尔
The HMS Carlisle is one of the ships.
我们不会对每一份情报都做出回应
We can't act on every piece of intelligence.
好吧，我们不会
So fine, we won't.
但这一份
Just this one.
彼得，你怎么了？
Peter, what's the matter with you?
我的哥哥..
My-my brother's...
那个，他在卡莱尔上
well, he's on the Carlisle.
他是海军射击少尉
A gunnery ensign.
我很..
I'm...
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
你觉得你自己是什么人？
Who the hell do you think you are?
那...那是我的哥哥
This... this is my brother.
他是我的大哥，没事，你还有
He's my big brother,all right, and you have
几分钟的时间可以救他
a few minutes to call off his murder.
我们不能
We can't.
他是对的
He's right.
艾伦
Alan.
琼
Joan.
休
Hugh.
约翰
John.
求你们了，我...
Please, I...
德军他们不会因为
The-the Germans, they won't get suspicious
这一起袭击起疑心的
just because we stop one attack.
没有人会知道的
No one will know.
我求你们了...
I'm asking you...
以你们朋友的身份
as your friend.
救救他吧
Please.
我很抱歉
I'm so sorry.
你不是上帝，艾伦...你没有权利决定
You're not God, Alan...you don't get to decide
谁生谁死
who lives and who dies.
不，我们可以
Yes, we do.
为什么？
Why?
因为再也没有其他人可以
Because no one else can.
你为什么告诉我这个？
Why are you telling me this?
我们需要你帮忙通过英国海军、空军、陆军
We need your help to keep this a secret from...
来隐藏这个秘密
Admiralty, Army, RAF.
呃，谁也不能知道我们破解了英格玛
Uh, no one can know we broke Enigma.
即使是丹尼斯顿也不能
Not even Denniston.
他正在考虑解雇你
Who's in the process of having you fired.
你可以处理好那个
You can take care of that.
虽然我们开发了一个系统来帮助你确定
While we develop a system to help you determine
哪些情报中的
how much intelligence
袭击...去阻止它发生
to act on... which a-attacks to stop,
哪些需要放弃
which to let through.
完全的统计分析
Statistical analysis.
希望用最少的攻击
The minimal number of actions
来赢得战争
it would take for us to win the war...
在德军起疑心之前
but the maximum number we can take
做出最多的攻击
before the Germans get suspicious.
所以你要相信这些数据统计是吗？
And you're going to trust all this to statistics?
- 对数学？           - 对的
- To maths?          - Correct.
然后军情六处要想出一个谎言
And then MI6 can come up with the lies
来告诉其他人
that we tell everybody else.
你需要一个可靠的情报来源
You'll need a believable alternative source for all
使它可以用在所有的情报上
the pieces of information you use.
一个我们能够解释我们的如何得到信息的虚假的故事
A false story so that we can explain how we got our information
而不是通过英格玛
that has nothing to do with Enigma.
然后你可以把这些故事泄漏给，额，德军
And then you can leak those stories to the, uh, the Germans.
然后是我们自己的军队
And then to our own military.
对最高级别的政府
Maintain a conspiracy of lies
散布一个阴谋谎言
at the highest levels of government.
听起来很对我胃口
Sounds right up my alley.
艾伦，我很少会这样说
Alan, I so rarely have cause to say this,
你正是我一直希望的那个人
but you are exactly the man I always hoped you would be.
他们代号命名为“最强者”
They code-named it "Ultra."
它为英国收集了最多的军事情报
It became the largest store of military intelligence
在，呃……世界历史上
in, uh...the history of the world.
就像在海因里希 希姆莱的对讲机里装了窃听器
It was like having a tap on Himmler's intercom.
I-E-O...
保密成为首要关注的问题
Secrecy became the primary concern,
因为某些原因，他们……他们信任我
and for some reason, they...they trusted me.
彼得…你有，呃
Peter... do you have the, uh,
那个630电译文...
the-the 630 decryp...
……是比尔密码
...it's a Beale cipher
加密来自一本书中的一句短语或…
encrypted with a phrase from a book or...
“求，就会给予汝
"Ask,and it will be given to you;
寻，就能寻见”马太福音第七章第七段
seek and you will find."Matthew 7:7.
这就是关键所在
That was the key.
彼得总有一天会回心转意的
Peter will come around eventually.
杰克
Jack.
能让我和艾伦单独呆会儿吗？
Could you give Alan and me a moment, please?
苏联和美国
The Soviets and us,
是我们站在同一边
we're on the same side.
我所做的事会帮助英国
What I'm doing will help Britain.
我要告诉丹尼斯顿
L-I have to tell Denniston.
不，你不会的
No, you don't.
因为如果你告诉他我的秘密…
Because if you tell him my secret...
我会告诉他你的
I'll tell him yours.
你知道他们会对同性恋怎么做吗？
Do you know what they do to homosexuals?
你永远不能再工作
You'll never be able to work again,
永远不能教书
never be able to teach.
你宝贵的机器…
Your precious machine...
我怀疑你会再也见不到他
I doubt you'll ever see him again.
你好，我可以...可以，额
Hello. Can I... can I, um,
和斯图尔特孟席斯通话吗？这是紧急的
speak to Stewart Menzies, please? It's urgent.
请稍候
One moment, please.
你好，孟席斯
Hello. Menzies.
关于保守秘密的一些建议
Some advice about keeping secrets.
就是尽量不发现他们的存在
It's a lot easier if you don't know them in the first place.
他们有在偷看我的信，窃听我的电话
Were they steaming my letters,tapping my telephone?
或跟踪我紧张的步伐吗？
Trailing my nervous walks?
你知道，我..
You know, I...
我从来没有发现
I never did find out.
琼？
Joan?
这是...
What's...
呃…
Uh...
琼在哪里？
where's Joan?
军事监狱
Military prison.
你做了什么？
What have you done?
一堆破译了的英格玛信息，我在床边的
Decoded Enigma intercepts.I found a pile of them
- 桌子上发现的               - 不，不，那些是我在
- in the bedside table.      - No, no. I-l gave those to her
一年前给她的当时我还在试图找出
over a year ago when I was trying to figure out
-这之间的联系…           -我相信你
- a link between...       - I'm sure you did.
丹尼斯顿一直在寻找一个苏联间谍
Denniston's been looking for a Soviet spy.
他认为在八组内部
He's been looking inside Hut 8.
我知道谁是间谍
I know who the spy is.
不是琼，是..
It's not Joan.It's...
凯恩 克罗斯
it's Cairncross.
我发现比尔密码的线索
L-I found the Beale cipher,
就是圣经
the Bible.
天啊，我希望你是一个间谍
God, I wish you'd been a spy.
你会比他强多了
You'd be so much better at this than he is.
你知道是他？
You knew it was him?
我当然知道
Of course I bloody knew.
他来 布莱奇利之前我就知道了
I knew before he came to Bletchley.
你认为我为什么把他放在这里？
Why do you think I had him placed here?
但我们只有一个英格玛密码机
But we have an Enigma machine.
是的，波兰情报局…
Yeah, Polish Intelligence...
你安排了
You-you placed
一个苏联特工在布莱奇利园？
a... a Soviet agent at Bletchley Park?
能够给斯大林透露我们想要
It's really quite useful to be able
透露的信息真是太好了
to leak whatever we want to Stalin.
丘吉尔太多疑了
Churchill's too damn paranoid.
他是不会透露一点关于
He won't share a shred of intelligence
苏联的情报
with the Soviets.
即使是能帮助他们对付德国的信息也不肯透露
Not even information that will help them against the Germans.
这有...
There's...
太多的秘密了
so much secrecy.
凯恩克罗斯不知道我们知道，肯定的
Cairncross has no idea we know, of course.
他不是什么聪明人
He's really not the brightest bulb.
这就是为什么我需要你的帮助
Which is why I need your help.
我想知道是什么泄漏给了约翰
I want to know what to leak to John,
苏联以及英国
what to feed to the Soviets,
得到了什么信息
as well as the British.
我..我不是间谍
I... I'm not a spy.
我..我只是一个数学家
I'm... I'm just a mathematician.
我认识很多间谍，艾伦
I know a lot of spies, Alan.
你有比他们更好的秘密
You've got more secrets than the best of them.
你…你要答应我，你会释放琼
You... you have to promise me that you will release Joan.
对了，琼在市场上
Yes, Joan's at the market.
她会在一小时后回来，之前我撒了谎
She's gonna be back in an hour. I lied.
这些我带走了
I better hold on to these.
如果有人发现了他们
If anybody finds out about them,
她可能真的要进监狱了
prison will be the least of her worries.
哦，艾伦…
Oh,Alan...
我们将会合作得很愉快
we're gonna have such a wonderful war together.
我要你离开这里
I need you to leave Bletchley.
-什么？      - 孟席斯，我不信任他
- What?     - It's Menzies. I don't trust him.
-这里不安全                 你认为还有哪里
-It's not safe here.        - Do you think it's any safer
- 比这更安全？        - 你需要离开
- anywhere else?       - You need to get away.
你需要远离我
You need to get very far away from me.
艾伦，发生什么事了？
Alan, what's happened?
我们不能订婚了
We can't be engaged anymore.
你…你的父母要你回去
You... your parents need to take you back
你会在那里找到你的丈夫的
and find you a husband elsewhere.
你怎么了？
What's wrong with you?
我有一件事，呃，呃，要告诉你
I have something, uh, uh, to tell you.
我..
I'm...
我是一个同性恋
I'm a homosexual.
好吧
All right.
不，我喜欢男人，琼…
No, no. M-Men, Joan...
呃，不是女人
uh, not women.
- 那又怎样？ -嗯
- So what?   - Well,
我刚刚告诉你了
I-I just told you.
我说那又怎样？
So what?
我有我的疑虑；我总是那样
I had my suspicions;I always did.
但我们不像其他人
But we're not like other people.
我们以我们自己的方式相爱者着
We love each other in our own way,
只要我们想就可以生活在一起
and we can have the life together that we want.
你-你…你不会是完美的丈夫
You-you... you won't be the perfect husband.
好吧，我可以告诉你
Well,I can promise you,
我也没想成为一个完美的妻子
I have no intention of being the perfect wife.
我不会...整天等你
I'll not be... fixing your lamb all day
下班回家
while you come home from the office.
我要工作
I'll work.
你也要工作
You'll work.
但我们拥有彼此的陪伴
And we'll have each other's company.
和彼此的心灵
We'll have each other's minds.
这听起来不像一个最美好的婚姻
That sounds like a better marriage than most.
但我在乎你
Because I care for you.
你在乎我
And you care for me.
我们可以比别人…
And we understand one another more than...
更多的了解彼此
more than anyone else ever has.
我没有
I don't.
-什么？   -在乎你
- What?  - Care for you.
我从来没有
I never did.
我只需要你破解英格玛
L-I just needed you to break Enigma.
现在我已经完成了，所以…所以你可以走了
I've done that now, so... so you can go.
我哪儿也不去
I'm not going anywhere.
我已经花了我太多的生命去
I've spent entirely too much of my life
担心你是怎么想我的
worried about what you think of me,
我父母是怎么想我
or what my parents think of me,
或者是八组的男生和三组的女生是怎么想我的
or the boys in Hut 8 or the girls in Hut 3.
你知道吗？我受够了
And do you know what? I'm done.
这是我能做的最重要的工作
This is the most important work I will ever do,
没有人能阻止我
and no one is going to stop me.
即便是你
Least of all, you.
你知道吗，他们是对的
You know what, they were right.
休，彼得，约翰
Peter, Hugh, John.
你真的是个混蛋
You really are a monster.
这场战争又持续了...
The war dragged on for two more...
两年...
solitary years...
我们每天都进行
and every day we performed
我们该死的演算
our blood-soaked calculus.
每一天我们都决定究竟谁死谁活
Every day we decided who lived and who died.
我们每一天…
Every day we...
都在帮助盟国打胜战，但没有人知道
helped the Allies to victories,and nobody knew.
斯大林格勒
Stalingrad.
阿登教授
The Ardenne.
诺曼底登陆
The invasion of Normandy.
所有的胜利如果我们提供得情报
All victories that would not have been possible
都是不可能发生的
without the intelligence that we supplied.
人们…
And people...
会谈论这场战争，这场，额...
talk about the war as this epic battle between, um...
文明...
civilizations...
自由与专制
freedom versus tyranny,
民主与纳粹的史诗般的战斗
democracy versus Nazism,
数百万人的军队
armies of millions
血流成河
bleeding into the ground,
船舰沉入海底
fleets of ships weighing down the oceans,
飞机从空中投下炸弹
planes dropping bombs from the sky
就像乌云一般遮挡住了太阳...
until they obliterated the sun itself...
但是战场对我们来说不是那样的
The war wasn't like that for us.
对我们来说，战场是...
For us, it was just...
...七八个填字游戏爱好者
...half a dozen crossword enthusiasts
住在英国南部一个的小村庄里
in a tiny village in the South of England.
这是…
This is...
你的胜利
your victory.
胜利…
Victory...
是属于每一片争取
of the cause of freedom
自由的土地
in every land.
这是一个庄严而光荣的时刻
This is a solemn but glorious hour.
我希望罗斯福总统
I wish that Franklin D. Roosevelt
能活着看到这一天
had lived to see this day.
我是上帝吗？
Was I God?
不，因为…
No. Because...
上帝没有赢得战争
God didn't win the war.
我们做到了
We did.
所以，现在怎么办？
So, what happens now?
难道...让我们都回到大学？
Is it... back to university for us, I suppose?
是的，差不多
Yes, pretty much.
但是你们剩下最后一件事情要
But you've one thing left to do
给你的政府服务
before your service to your government
- 服务              - 是什么？
- in concluded.     - What's that?
烧掉一切
Burn everything.
- 烧掉?为什么？   -在你们开始的时候
- Burn? Why?      - You were told when you started
说过这是一个绝密计划……你认为我们在开玩笑吗？
This was a top-secret program...did you think we were joking?
- 但是战争已经结束             -只是这场而已
- But the war is over.         - This war is.
但还会有其他战争的
But there'll be others.
而且我们知道如何破译
And we know how to break a code
大家都认为牢不可破的密码
that everybody else believes is unbreakable.
正是如此
Precisely.
尘归尘，土归土
Tear it down.Light it up.
忘掉该忘的
Sweep away the ashes.
你从来没有见过
None of you have ever met before.
你从来没有听说过英格玛这个词
None of you have ever even heard the word Enigma.
回家一路顺风
Have a safe trip home.
另外，运气好的话，你永远不会
Behave. With a bit of luck, you'll never have
在你的余生见到我或者是其他人
to see me or one another again for the rest of your lives.
难以置信
That's unbelievable.
现在，警探
Now, Detective,
你来判断
you get to judge.
告诉我…
So, tell me...
我是什么？
what am I?
嗯，我是..
Mm, am I...
机器？
a machine?
还是人类？
Am I a person?
我是一个战争英雄？
Am I a war hero?
还是一个罪犯？
Am I a criminal?
我无法判断
I can't judge you.
好吧，那么…
Well, then...
……你一点也没有帮到我
...you're no help to me at all.
进来
Come in.
你要见我吗，先生？
You wanted to see me, sir?
图灵，请坐
Turing. Sit down.
发生什么事了吗？
Something the matter?
听说你和克里斯托弗莫科姆走得很近
You and Christopher Morcom are quite close.
我不好说
I wouldn't say that.
嗯，你的数学老师
Well, your mathematics teacher
说你们两个形影不离
says the two of you are positively inseparable.
我们班里最好的学生
We're the best students in the class.
那天他抓住你们传纸条了
He caught you passing notes the other day.
密码学，用来打发时间的，那节课太简单了
Cryptography, to pass the time. The class is too simple.
你和你的朋友在数学课堂用数学来解决问题
You and your friend solve maths problems during maths class
是因为数学课太无聊了？
because the maths class is too dull?
他不是我的朋友
He's not my friend.
好吧，我听说他是你唯一的朋友
Well, I'm told he's your only friend.
谁说的？
Who said that?
关于莫科姆发生了一些事
Something's come up concerning Morcom.
我为什么在这里？
Why am I here?
克里斯托弗去世了
Christopher is dead.
我不明白
I don't understand.
他的母亲今天早上派人送来的消息
His mother sent word this morning.
他们一家人在度假，你知道的
The family were on holiday, you see.
我不理解
I don't understand.
嗯，他有牛结核病
Well, he had bovine tuberculosis,
我相信他告诉过你
as I'm sure he told you.
所以一切不是那么突然，但是...
So this won't come as a shock, but...
仍然，同样的
still, all the same,
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
你搞错了
You're mistaken.
他没告诉你吗？
Did he not tell you?
嗯，他已经病了很长时间
Well, he's been sick for a long time.
他知道这是必然的
He knew this was coming soon.
但他还咬是坚持来上课
But he had a stiff upper lip about it.
真是个好孩子
Good lad.
-你没事吧，图灵？                   -是的，当然
- Are you all right, Turing?        - Yes. Of course.
就像我说的，我不是很了解他
Like I said,I didn't know him very well.
啊，我知道了
Ah. I see.
那好吧
Very well.
我可以走了吗，校长？
May I leave, Headmaster?
恭喜你，长官
Congratulations, sir.
对不起
Sorry.
我会出庭的
I would have come.
我会帮你作证
I would have testified.
那你要说些什么，我，呃…
And what would you have said,that I, uh...
我不是同性恋
I wasn't a homosexual.
艾伦…这是很严重的事
Alan... this is serious.
他们会送你去监狱的
They could send you to jail.
该死的
Damn it.
你的手在抽搐
Your hands.You're twitching.
不不，我没有
No-no, I'm not.
-艾伦    -额…
- Alan.  - Uh...
是药物治疗
It's the medication.
药物治疗？
The medication?
额，嗯，法官给了我，嗯，一个选择…
Uh, well, the judge gave me, um, a choice...
呃，是-是要两年监禁
uh, ei-either two years in prison
还是…荷-荷尔蒙治疗
or... ho-hormonal therapy.
哦，我的天啊
Oh, my God.
是的，是的，没错
Yes, yes, that's right.
化学阉割
Chemical castration.
嗯，用来，嗯，用来治愈我的，嗯…
Um, to, uh, to cure me of my, um...
同性恋的嗜好
homosexual predilections.
嗯，我当然选择这个
Well, of course I chose that.
我的意思是，我...无法...
I mean, I... couldn't...
在监狱里工作，而且，额...
work in prison, and, uh...
好吧
All right.
现在，我要去找你的医生谈谈
Now, I-I'm going to speak to your doctors.
- 还有你的律师                             -我没事
- I'm going to speak to your lawyers.      - I'm-I'm fine.
- 请让我来帮助你                - 不，我，呃，不需要你的帮助
- Please let me help you.       - No, I, uh, don't need your help,
谢谢
thank you.
艾伦，你不必独自一人去承受
Alan, you do not have to do this alone.
我不是一个人
I'm not alone.
从来不是
Never have been.
克里斯托弗将会变得更加智能
Christopher's become so smart.
如果我不持续的治疗，
If-if I don't continue my treatment,
然后他们会，嗯…
then they'll, um...
……他们会把他从我身边带走
...they'll take him away from me.
你…
You...
你不能让他们这么做，你不能
You-you can't let them do that. You can't.
你…你不能让他们把他带走
You... you can't let them leave me alone.
我不...我不想一个人
I don't...I don't want to be alone.
- 我不想一个人                 - 没...没事的，都会没事的
- I don't want to be alone.    - All ri... all right, all right.
都会好起来的
All right.
一切都会好起来的，过来坐下
It's all right.Come and sit down.
都会好起来的
It's all right.
过来休息下
Come and sit down.
一切都会没事的
It's all right.
哦，嗯，这个..
Oh, well, that's a...
这个是个漂亮的戒指
that's a much nicer ring
比我给你的那个好多了
than the one I-l made you.
是的，他的名字是杰克
Yes. His name's Jock.
他是个军人
He's an Army man,
如果你能相信的话
if you can believe it.
我们在一起工作
We work together.
我们为什么不做填字游戏呢
Why don't we do a crossword puzzle.
它只会花费我们五分钟
It'll only take us five minutes.
或者，以你的要求，六分钟
Or, in your case, six.
给你
There.
呃…
Uh...
嗯，也..也许以后吧
Uh, p... perhaps later.
好的，当然
Yes, of course.
你得到了你想要的，不是吗？
You-you got what you wanted, didn't you?
工作，一个丈夫
Work, a husband.
平凡的生活
Normal life.
没有一个平凡人能做到那样
No one normal could have done that.
你知道吗，今天早上…
Do you know, this morning...
我在火车上
I was on a train
经过一个城市，如果不是因为你
that went through a city that wouldn't exist
它将是不存在的
if it wasn't for you.
我从一个男人那买了一张票
I bought a ticket from a man
如果不是因为你他可能已经死了
who would likely be dead if it wasn't for you.
我所
I read up
工作的…
on my work...
整个科学探索领域
a whole field of scientific inquiry
只因你而存在
that only exists because of you.
现在，如果你真的希望你可以变得平凡…
Now, if you wish you could have been normal...
我可以向你保证我没有
I can promise you I do not.
这个世界是无限美好的地方
The world is an infinitely better place
正是因为你的不平凡
precisely because you weren't.
你…
Do you...
你真的这么认为？
do you really think that?
我认为…
I think...
有时候正是人们
that sometimes it is the people
意想不到之人
who no one imagines anything of
做出了人们
who do the things
意想不到之事
that no one can imagine.
在持续了一年的强制治疗之后,
图灵于1954年6月7日自杀身亡
享年41岁
在1885-1967年间,
大约49000同性恋依照英国法律被判有罪
2013年，伊丽莎白女王为图灵赦免
以此对他前所未有的贡献表示敬意
历史学家认为英格玛密码的破解使二战缩短了至少两年
拯救了超过一千四百万人的生命
这些秘密被政府保管50年后公开
图灵的工作鼓舞了几代人投入到被科学界称为“图灵机”的研究当中
今天我们叫它“电脑”